Contact

www.linkedin.com/in/ debashishghosh1 (LinkedIn) debashishghosh1.wixsite.com/hr-eday (Blog)

Top Skills

Employee Engagement
Performance Management
BPO

Languages

English, Hindi, Bengali, Assamese (Full Professional)

Certifications

Personality & Ability Assessment and OPQ32

GLA360 (A leadership 360 assessment tool)

Certified Emotional Intelligence Practitioner (EQ-i 2.0 & EQ360)

Six Sigma Green Belt

Instructional Design and Facilitation Skills

Honors-Awards

Global Operations Leadership Development (GOLD) Program

Publications

Trends to look forward in 2018 – Employee Trust

Debashish Ghosh

VP and Country HR Head, Berkadia (a Berkshire Hathaway and Jefferies Financial Group Co.) | Coach | Speaker | Mentor for B-Schools & Students

Hyderabad

Summary

I am a senior Human Resources professional with over 18 years of experience in managing end-to-end functions in HR. Over these years, I have helped organizations attain business outcomes by realizing the true potential of their human capital. I have led and driven many transformational and organizational development initiatives through the right blend of deep functional expertise, modern technology and change management skills. I practice and rely on advanced HR analytics to gain insights and calculate RoI of various people initiatives.

I am currently working as the Vice President and Head of HR, for Berkadia Services India Pvt. Ltd. This is the Indian subsidiary of Berkadia Commercial Mortgage LLC (www.berkadia.com), a Berkshire Hathaway and Jefferies Financial Services Co. Prior to joining Berkadia, I was associated with GE and Genpact managing multiple roles in HR.

I am an Executive Alumnus of IIM Calcutta and a Marshall Goldsmith Certified Executive and Teams Coach. I have been awarded with two of the most prestigious HR credentials in the world - Senior Certified Professional® from Society of Human Resources Management (SHRM-SCP®), and Global Talent Management Leader (GTML™) from Talent Management Institute. Being certified practitioners of DISC, MBTI® and EQ-i 2.0® (behavior and personality assessment tools), I help organizations identify potential strengths and blind spots of their workforce. I am a Certified NLP Practitioner, awarded by the International NLP Association.

Strategic Academia-Corporate partnership has impact on talent management and, consequently, on business outcomes. To that effect, I engage closely with B-schools in several ways which includes mentoring programs, Masterclasses, advising on the curriculum and selecting new MBA batches.

I am an active member of 2 premier HR associations – SHRM and HRFI. In this capacity, I work closely with policymakers and industry peers to track the latest trends impacting businesses. I exchange ideas and thoughts through my speaking assignments, by blogging and through LinkedIn posts.

I am an avid reader (please follow my Instagram account Debashish.ghosh1 for book recommendations) and like to travel. Fitness is my other passion, specially running. I am currently training to run a half-marathon under 2hr 20 min.

Experience

Berkadia

2 years 11 months

Vice President and Head - Human Rescources, Berkadia India February 2019 - Present (1 year 7 months)

Hyderabad Area, India

- Work closely with the senior management and spearhead the HR function for the organization and focused on transformation and change management from a services-based to a product development company
- Plan and develop a strategic approach, policies and initiatives to meet the talent acquisition targets without compromising in the quality of hire.
- Identify behavioral competencies that would drive business performance; create and implement a strategy for capability building of employees at all levels
- Design a compensation structure in line with the industry practices which drives employee and organizational performance

Assistant Vice President - Human Resources October 2017 - January 2019 (1 year 4 months) Hyderabad Area, India

Berkadia, a joint venture of Berkshire Hathaway and Jefferies Financial Group Inc., is an industry leading commercial real estate company providing comprehensive capital solutions and investment sales advisory and research services for multifamily and commercial properties. Berkadia is amongst the largest, highest rated and most respected primary, master and special servicers in the industry.

GENPACT, Hyderabad

11 years 3 months

Assistant Vice President, Human Resources December 2014 - September 2017 (2 years 10 months)

Hyderabad Area, India

- * Led the HR and L&D functions for a portfolio of 12 client accounts, over 3 locations and 1500+ employees.
- * Developed and implemented HR strategies and goals that align with and support the same for the organization. Provided HR leadership with timely and accurate information required for strategic decision-making.
- * Designed and oversaw employee performance management systems that meet the organization's talent management needs. Regularly monitored results against performance standards and goals and advised the organization on succession planning of key roles.
- * Establishes and monitors criteria for organizational compliance with statutory employment laws and regulations. Coached and counselled managers on how to operate within the parameters of organizational policy, labor agreements and employment agreements. Worked with Government officials whenever necessary.
- * Administered and supported HR practices and policies that identify and/or mitigate workplace risk. Ensured that risk management activities and plans are audited and that the results inform risk mitigation strategies.
- * Implemented strategies to ensure that appropriate workforce staffing levels and competencies exist to meet the organization's goals. Coordinated with business leaders to create strategies that address the organization's leadership needs.

Senior Manager Human Resources
October 2011 - November 2014 (3 years 2 months)
Hyderabad Area, India

- * Analyzed staffing levels and projections to forecast workforce needs. Designed and developed effective strategies for sourcing, recruiting and evaluating qualified job candidates for acquiring a workforce to meets the organization's needs.
- * Developed and implemented HR best practices for employee retention and engagement. Coached supervisors on creating positive working relationships with their employees. Monitored the organization's metrics on employee

engagement, turnover and retention and communicated to other senior leaders on the same.

- * Designed and oversaw employee performance management systems that meet the organization's talent management needs. Regularly monitored results against performance standards and goals and advised the organization on succession planning of key roles.
- * Evaluated gaps in employees' competencies and skills and used best practices to develop and deliver learning and development activities that closed those gaps. Created long-term strategies to develop talent in collaboration with supervisors and employees. Monitored the effectiveness of programs for emerging leaders and leadership development.
- * Ensured compliance to organizational compensation and benefits philosophies, strategies and plans. Designed and developed effective variable incentive plans for talent retention and management.
- Consulted the business leadership on designing organizational structures that align with the effective delivery of activities in support of the business goals. Assessed organizational needs to identify critical competencies for operational effectiveness.

Assistant Manager - Manager, Human Resources July 2006 - October 2011 (5 years 4 months) Hyderabad Area, India

- * Conducted engagement surveys and coordinated focus group discussions in order to gauge employee perceptions and opinions.
- * Designed job descriptions to meet the organization's resource needs. Implemented effective onboarding and orientation programs for new employees.
- * Designed and implemented Reward and Recognition programs in line with the goals and objectives of the business
- * Created individual development plans (IDPs) in collaboration with supervisors and employees. Administered and monitored programs to promote knowledge transfer.
- Implemented the organization's strategies on appropriate pay, benefit, incentive, separation and severance systems and programs.
- * Worked effectively with contractual employees and vendors oversaw their efficiency and monitored their effectiveness against costs.
- * Consulted managers on how to supervise difficult employees, handle disruptive behaviors and respond with the appropriate level of corrective action.

- * Effectively communicated HR programs, practices and policies to both HR and non-HR employees.
- * Monitored changes in turnover and retention metrics, and ensures that leadership is aware of such changes.
- * Developed and implemented workplace policies, handbooks and codes of conduct.

GE

Management Trainee, Accounts Receivables April 2001 - June 2005 (4 years 3 months)

Hyderabad Area, India

Led the Accounts receivables operations of a US based Transportation major with prime responsibilities of:

- * Led a team of 25 accounts receivables professionals responsible of collecting past dues of 2 regions in the US
- * Maintained the past due receivables of below 6% month-on-month highlight risk and issues proactively and implement mitigation plan
- * Ensured minimum calls coverage per day in addition to management of escalated issues/calls with focus on maximizing client/customer satisfaction.
- * Drove continuous process improvements within the team.
- * Managed retention in the team at over 85% year-on-year
- * Conducted line interviews for selection of new hires in the team

Dolphin Hotel - Visakhapatnam Guest Relations Executive October 1998 - March 2001 (2 years 6 months)

Vishakhapatnam Area, India

- * Retention of existing customers; leading group check-ins in addition to management of VIP guests and sending of personalized correspondence to customers.
- * Management and redressal of customer concerns/grievances with the aim of maximizing customer satisfaction.
- * Also involved in shift management to ensure optimum utilization of available resources leading to smooth functioning of operations.

Education

Indian Institute of Management, Calcutta
LEAD - Advanced Management Program (2019 - 2020)

XLRI Jamshedpur Executive Certificate Program, Human Resources Management

Indian Institute of Management Rohtak Advanced HR Analytics

Indian Institute Of Business Management And Studies Master of Business Administration (MBA), Human Resources

Osmania University BA, Psychology